<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 21:17:03 +0000</pubDate><title>About</title><url>about</url><meta></meta><metad></metad><menu>About</menu><menuOrder>2</menuOrder><menuStatus>Y</menuStatus><template>nosidebar.php</template><parent></parent><content>&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;about-image&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img alt=&amp;quot;Meredith Madon&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;/data/uploads/meri.png&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Meredith (Meri) served as a lawyer for students with special needs from 2005-2024. During her work she found that cranio sacral therapy, SomatoEmotion release and shamanic work was a surprisingly effective and efficient way of healing emotional trauma and calming the nervous system. Having a background working the children with special needs she decided to study the healing modalities.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In March 2000 Meri received a New York State License in Massage Therapy. She completed advanced training in cranio sacral therapy, SomatoEmotion Release, and Pediatrics at the Upledger International Institute from 2019-2025. She studied Dynamic Body Balancing with Susan Teiche in 2024. From 2016-2018 she completed 5 levels of training in cranio sacral therapy, SomatoEmotion release and Shamanic work with Natalie Kasdan and Annie Samojedney. She studied Reiki level III with Gretchen Avery in 1997. She completed a course in Visceral Manipulation with the Barral Institute in 2025.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Meri is currently in a 3 year Residential Program with The Foundation for Shamanic Studies. Prior to entering the program she completed various courses in core shamanism with the foundation.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Meri graduated with a B.S. &amp;quot;with Honors&amp;quot; from Cornell University in 1999 and obtained a J.D. from the University of California, Berkeley in 2004. Prior to entering law school, Meri completed a Fulbright Scholarship focusing on the study of disabilities and special education for which she received a Masters of Education in Special Education. Meri taught briefly in the New York City Public Schools and spent years as a camp counselor for students with special needs.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
</content><private></private><author>lilly</author><customField_categoryName/><customField_categoryLink/><customField_subcardQuestion/></item>
